A Finding Aid to the Mark di Suvero and di Suvero Family Papers, 1934-2005, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers
1934-2005
Archives of American Art
Di Suvero, Mark, 1933-
AAA.disumark
Archival Resource Key
6.8 Linear feet
0.263 Gigabytes
The collection measures 6.8 linear feet and 0.263 GB, dates from 1934 to 2005, and documents the career of sculptor Mark di Suvero and family relationships. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters to and from di Suvero family members; scattered writings by di Suvero and Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister, about Mark di Suvero; drawings; a file on the Socrates Sculpture Park; a file on artist Helen Lessick, an acquaintance of Mark di Suvero; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of the artist, artwork, and members of the di Suvero family; audio and video recordings of interviews with di Suvero; and promotional Tee Shirts. There is an unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2022 that includes a WordPerfect transcript in electronic format of an unpublished play Crescent Moon, Yellow Star, but Henry (Hank) di Suvero, 2004.
Biographical Note
Mark di Suvero was born September 18, 1933, in Shanghai, China, the son of Matilde Millo di Suvero and Victor E. di Suvero, an Italian diplomat. He was one of four children: Victor M., the eldest, Marie Louise, Mark, and the youngest son Henry. With the outbreak of World War II, the family immigrated to San Francisco, California, in 1941.
Mark di Suvero studied fine arts and philosophy at the San Francisco City College from 1953 to 1954, and attended the University of California, Santa Barbara, from 1954-1955, where he began creating sculpture. In 1956, he received a B.A. in Philosophy from the University of California, Berkeley. The following year, di Suvero moved to New York City to establish a career as a sculptor.
Shortly before his first solo exhibition at the Green Gallery in 1960, di Suvero suffered severe spinal injuries when he was pinned against an elevator shaft in a construction accident. Initially confined to a wheelchair for two years, di Suvero persevered in overcoming his injuries and continuing his work.
In protest of the Vietnam War, di Suvero left the United States in 1971, and exhibited his sculpture in Holland and Germany. A year later, he established a painting and drawing studio in Venice, where he also taught at the Università Internazionale dell'Arte, and, in 1973, he moved to France. Also during this time, di Suvero married Maria Teresa Capparotta, an architect, whom he later divorced.
The Whitney Museum of American Art honored Mark di Suvero in 1975 with the first retrospective and first American city-wide exhibition of his work, in New York City. At this time, di Suvero began working with a team in assembling his sculpture, first with Lowell McKegney, and later joined by his nephews Enrico and Matteo Martignoni.
In 1977, di Suvero founded the Athena Foundation to award grants to artists. In 1986, in conjunction with the Athena Foundation and with Enrico Martignoni, he created the Socrates Sculpture Park in Long Island City, New York, an outdoor space where sculptors are invited to create and exhibit their work. With Marcel Evrard in 1988, di Suvero created a foundation entitled La Vie des Formes (The Life of Forms) in the shipyards at Chalon-sur-Saône, France. Based upon the model of Socrates Sculpture Park, this organization hosted artists in studio and exhibition spaces at the shipyard and on di Suvero's converted canal barge Rêve des Signes, that was moored alongside.
Included in most major international gallery collections, Mark di Suvero's art work has also been the focus of major solo exhibitions including two at Storm King, and international city-wide exhibitions in Duisberg and Stuttgart in Germany, Chalon-sur-Saône, Paris, Valence, and Nice in France, and Valencia in Spain. During the summer of 1995, di Suvero was honored with a major installation of seven pieces along the Grand Canal to coincide with the Venice Biennale's 100th anniversary.
In 1993, Mark di Suvero married Kate Levin, Ph.D., a professor at the City University of New York and Commissioner of the New York Department of Cultural Affairs. Di Suvero and Levin have a daughter named Veri. At present, di Suvero maintains studios in Petaluma, California, Long Island City, New York, and Chalon-sur-Saône, France.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 6.8 linear feet and 0.263 GB, dates from 1934 to 2005, and documents the career of sculptor Mark di Suvero and the importance of his family relationships. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters to and from di Suvero family members; scattered writings by di Suvero and Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister, about Mark di Suvero; drawings; a file on the Socrates Sculpture Park; a file on artist Helen Lessick, a friend of Mark di Suvero; exhibition files; printed material; photographs of the artist, artwork, and members of the di Suvero family; audio and video recordings of interviews with di Suvero; and promotional Tee Shirts.
There is an unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2022 that includes a WordPerfect transcript in electronic format of an unpublished play Crescent Moon, Yellow Star, but Henry (Hank) di Suvero, 2004.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into 12 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1941-2004 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1956-2005, undated (Boxes 1, 6-8, 11-12, OV 10; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1961-2005, undated (Boxes 1, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Drawings, 1983, undated (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 5: Socrates Sculpture Park File, 1985-2004, undated (Boxes 1-2, 7; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Helen Lessick File, 1986-2004 (Box 2, 7; 6 folders)
Series 7: Exhibition Files, 1975-2003 (Boxes 2-3, 7; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1958-2004, undated (Box 3-4, 7, OV 9; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, 1934-2004, undated (Box 4-6, 0.263 GB; ER01; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 10: Audio and Video Recordings, 1982-1994, undated (Box 5; 7 folders)
Series 11: Promotional Tee Shirts, 1978-2001 (Box 7; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 12: Unprocessed 2022 Addition, 2004
All series have been arranged chronologically.
Provenance
The Mark di Suvero and di Suvero family papers were donated in 2004 and 2005 by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, the artist's sister. One transcript of a play by Henry di Suvero was donated in 2022 by Henry (Hank) di Suvero's estate, via Scott Krauss, co-executor.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Drawings; Photographs; Works of art; Sound recordings; Interviews; Video recordings; Slides (photographs); Lessick, Helen; Socrates Sculpture Park
- Biographical Material, 1941-2004; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of biographical accounts for various members of the di Suvero family and school records for Mark di Suvero. The curricula vitae were written by Mark di Suvero.
  - Biographical Accounts for di Suvero Family Members, 1993-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae Written by Mark di Suvero, 1984-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Report Cards for Mark di Suvero, 1941-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - School Attendance Certificate for Mark di Suvero, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters, 1956-2005, undated; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1, 6-8, 11-12, OV 10
  Letters are primarily from family members, friends, and colleagues.
  - Letters from di Suvero Family Members, 1966-2005, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-32)
  - Letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, ACCESS RESTRICTED, circa 1941-circa 1956; 1956-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1-38)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Letters from Mark di Suvero to his brother, Henry, circa 1941-2001 are access restricted; written permission is required. Contact Reference Services for more information.
  - Letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, ACCESS RESTRICTED, 1991-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1-18)
  - Oversized letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, ACCESS RESTRICTED, 1958-1999, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
  - Oversized letters from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, ACCESS RESTRICTED, 1972, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 10)
  - Letters from Mark di Suvero to Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, 1983 September-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversized letter from Mark di Suvero to Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
- Notes and Writings, 1961-2005, undated; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1, 6
  This series primarily consists of Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero's notes and writings. The files containing notes for her lecture at the University of New Mexico include 2 photographs and 80 slides of Mark di Suvero's art work. There are also writings by Mark, Henry, and Victor di Suvero.
  - Poems by Mark di Suvero, 1961, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Typescripts of Poems Written from 1938 to 1953 by Victor di Suvero, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Notes and Writings by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero, 1982-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Draft Press Release for the Portland Museum, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Notes for Lecture at University of New Mexico, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Proposal to Cast in Bronze Gutzon Borglum's Bust of Adolph Bandelier, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Notes Concerning Mark di Suvero Art Work Executed Between 1954 and 2004, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous Notes Concerning Decades of Family Events, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40-45)
- Drawings, 1983, undated; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1
  Three small ink sketches by Mark di Suvero are designs for sculpture.
  - Ink Sketches, 1983, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Socrates Sculpture Park File, 1985-2004, undated; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 7
  This series contains material concerning the Socrates Sculpture Park, an outdoor space where sculptors are invited to create and exhibit their work, created through the Athena Foundation. The photographs include one showing New York Mayor Koch presenting co-founder Enrico Martignoni with an award for the Park. Artifacts include two matchbooks and a tee shirt advertising the Park.
  - Letters, 1985-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - Typescript of the Proposal, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Inventory and Analysis Report, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Notes and Writings, 1986-2001, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Clippings, 1985-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
  - Press Packet, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous Press Releases, 1986-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs (see also Box 7), 1986-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56-64)
  - Brochure for the Athena Foundation, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Brochures for Socrates Sculpture Park, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66-67)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1986-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Photographs, 1986-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Videotape Socrates Sculpture Park, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artifacts (see Also Box 7), 2003, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcement from the Socrates Sculpture Park File, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Socrates Sculpture Park tee shirt, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
- Helen Lessick File, 1986-2004; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Boxes 2, 7
  This series contains miscellaneous material relating to artist Helen Lessick, an Athena grant-funded artist and friend of Mark di Suvero and the Martignoni family, who exhibited her work at the Socrates Sculpture Park in its early days, and at Chalon-sur-Saône's La Vie des Formes.
  - Letters (see also Box 7), 1990-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1987-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1986-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Baseball Cards Created by Helen Lessick, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bookmarks Created by Helen Lessick, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Illustrated Letter from Helen Lessick File, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
- Exhibition Files, 1975-2003; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 7; (Box 2-3, 7; 1.4 linear feet)
  The exhibition files contain miscellaneous material relating to specific exhibitions or installations by Mark di Suvero. Most files contain printed materials, catalogs, announcements, notes, a few essays, letters, and photographs. Two of the exhibition files also contain video recordings: La Biennale di Venezia, XLCI International Art Exhibition, Venice, Italy, 1994-1996; Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York, 1995-1996.
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, New York, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-14)
  - Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-21)
  - Württembergischer Kunstverein, Stuttgart, Germany, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - Musée des Beaux-Arts, Valence, France, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27-36)
  - Musée d'Art Moderne et d'Art Contemporain, Nice, France, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
  - Unveiling of L'Illume (Erleuchtung), Parliament Building, Bonn, Germany, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41-45)
  - Centre Julio González, Valencian Institute of Modern Art (IVAM), Valencia, Spain, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - La Biennale di Venezia, XLCI International Art Exhibition, Venice, Italy, 1994-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47-53)
  - Dedication of Sea Change, South Beach Park, San Francisco, California, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54-60)
  - Storm King Art Center, Mountainville, New York, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Mark di Suvero in Paris Exhibition, Paris, France, 1997-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-15)
  - Unveiling of Tyne Anew, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Works from a Private Collection, Danese Gallery, New York, New York, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
  - Installation of Beppe, University of Missouri at St. Louis and Laumeier Sculpture Park, St. Louis, Missouri, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21-25)
  - Oversized Letter from Mark di Suvero to Henry di Suvero, from the La Biennale di Venezia Exhibition File, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Oversized Posters from a Press Packet in Exhibition File for Mark di Suvero in Paris, 1997; Archival Resource Key
- Printed Material, 1958-2004, undated; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 7, OV 9
  This series consists of printed material that does not directly relate to specific exhibitions. Exhibition announcements include a poster for di Suvero's first solo exhibition at the Green Gallery in 1960. Exhibition catalogs for The Hands, 1996-1997, and for the Orange County Museum of Art solo exhibition, 1998, are autographed.
  - Clippings (see also Box 7), 1960-2004, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26-58)
  - Press Releases, 1966-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Mark di Suvero (see also OV 9), 1958-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 60-68)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Mark di Suvero, 1987-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others (see also Box 7), 1976-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - Lecture Announcements, 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Brochures for Miscellaneous Art Galleries, 1973-2004, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23-26)
  - Brochures for the Sale of Art Work, 1973-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Travel Brochures, 1990-1995, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1991-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Note Cards with Photographs of Art Work by Mark di Suvero, 1996-2001, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Postcards with Photographs of Art Work by Mark di Suvero, 1998, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Picture Postcards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Booklet Summer War Haiku by Jack Crimmins, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Book New York Painting and Sculpture: 1940-1970 by Henry Geldzahler, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1993-2000, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1964-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcement for Others, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcements for Mark di Suvero, 1960-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 9)
- Photographs, 1934-2004, undated; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 4-6; 0.264 Gigabytes ER01
  Photographs are of Mark di Suvero, members of the di Suvero family, di Suvero's studios and art work. Many of the photographs depict a combination of all these elements, so they have been organized into one chronology in order to maintain the sense of each occasion. The slides, found here also in digital format, of di Suvero's work belonged to friend and dealer Richard Bellamy.
  - Photographs of the di Suvero Family and Mark di Suvero's Art Work, 1934-2004; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 4, Folder 36-49)
  - Statement regarding Slides and Digital Images of Mark di Suvero's Art Work Executed from the 1960s to 1990s, 2004; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mark di Suvero's Art Work Executed from the 1960s to 1990s, Digital Images, 2004; Archival Resource Key; 0.263 Gigabytes 183 computer files (Folder ER01)
  - Mark di Suvero's Art Work Executed from the 1960s to 1990s, Slides, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
- Audio and Video Recordings, 1982-1994, undated; Series 10; Archival Resource Key; 7 Folders Box 5
  This series presents aural and visual insights into Mark di Suvero's work. With the exception of La Vie des Formes, all videotapes contain interviews of Mark di Suvero.
  - Audio-Cassette Lecture by Marie Louise Martignoni di Suvero Speaking about Mark di Suvero, Portland Museum of Art, Oregon, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Videotape Mark di Suvero: Rêve des Signes (Dream of Signs), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Videotape Storm King, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Videotape La Vie des Formes by Dominique Evrard, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Videotape In the Steel: A Portrait of Mark di Suvero, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Videotape Sculptors at Storm King, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Videotape Echt Wahr Träume (Genuinely True Dreams) by Nina Hagar, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Promotional Tee Shirts, 1978-2001; Series 11; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 7
  These Tee Shirts are promotional items from an unveiling event for Mark di Suvero's sculpture Potowatami, and from a charity event.
  - Tee Shirt from the Unveiling of Potowatami, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Tee Shirt from the Art Walk 2001 for the Venice Family Clinic, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)